## SARA NG

Department of Linguistics University of Washington sbng@uw.edu
sarablalockng.github.io

### SUMMARY

I am interested in the way humans create, modify, and perceive speech sounds, especially in the way that prosodic cues. My research goals are to integrate the unique information found in speech prosody into modern methods for natural language processing and generation. I am primarily interested in computational models of prosody and dialogue management in dyadic and multiparty conversation. For example, I have used prosodic signals to recover punctuation in speech transcripts, and used computational techniques to model speaker entrainment and conversational dynamics. I have also investigated the differential use of perceptual speech cues by listeners with hearing loss, and develop methods for identifying listener behavior in a clinical environment.

I am a member of the Transformation, Interpretation, and Analysis of Language (TIAL) Lab in the Department of Electrical Engineering and the Phonetics Lab in the Department of Linguistics at the University of Washington, and my dissertation research is in collaboration with the Hearing Aid Laboratory at Northwestern University and CLILLAC-ARP at Université Paris Cité.

#### **EDUCATION**

current University of Washington

Ph.D. candidate: Linguistics

Advised by Drs. Richard Wright and Mari Ostendorf **Masters of Science**: Computational Linguistics

2013-2017 University of Utah

Honors Bachelor of Arts: Linguistics

Advisor: Dr. Abby Kaplan

Thesis: Musical Text-Setting as Evidence for Syllabification of Highly Moraic Structures in English

Bachelor of Science: Applied Mathematics

**TESOL**: Teaching English to Students of Other Languages Certificate

### **PUBLICATIONS**

2023 Sara Ng, Abigail Schwendiman Sleight

Properties of Constructed Language Phonological Inventories University of Washington Working Papers in Linguistics

2022 Yeonjin Cho, Sara Ng, Trang Tran, Mari Ostendorf

Leveraging Prosody for Punctuation Prediction of Spontaneous Speech

INTERSPEECH

2022 Andrew Hard, Kurt Partridge, Neng Chen, Sean Augenstein, Aishanee Shah, Hyun Jin Park,

Alex Park, Sara Ng, Jessica Nguyen, Ignacio Lopez Moreno, and others

Production federated keyword spotting via distillation, filtering, and joint federated-centralized training

INTERSPEECH

2021 Sara Ng, Gregory M. Ellis, Pamela E. Souza, Frederick J. Gallun, Richard A. Wright, Mari Ostendorf

Assessing the stability of the spectro-temporal cue weighting angle for listener categorization

Proceedings of Meetings on Acoustics

2021 Courtney Mansfield, **Sara Ng**, Gina-Anne Levow, Richard Wright, Mari Ostendorf Revisiting Parity of Human vs. Machine Conversational Speech Transcription INTERSPEECH

### PAPERS IN PREPARATION

- Marina Oganyan, Gina-Anne Levow, Robert Squizzero, Emily P. Ahn, **Sara Ng**, Ella Deaton, Richard A. Wright
  - $Investigating\ the\ Acoustic\ Fidelity\ of\ Vowels\ across\ Remote\ Recording\ Methods\ submitted\ to\ Linguistics\ Vanguard$
- Sara Ng, Calvin Murdock, Vamsi Krishna Ithapu, Jeff Crukley, Christi Miller Inferring Hearing Impairment through Dialogue Dynamics and Speech Content in preparation

### PRESENTATIONS

- 2021 Courtney Mansfield, **Sara Ng** Gina-Anne Levow, Mari Ostendorf, Richard Wright
  What does parity mean? A detailed comparison of ASR and human transcription errors
  Acoustical Society of America, **talk**
- 2018 Sara Ng, Joselyn Roriguez and Abby Kaplan
  Musical Evidence for Syllabification Patterns of Highly Moraic Structures in English
  Linguistic Society of America, poster
- 2017 Jenica Jessen, **Sara Ng** and Joselyn Rodriguez

  Musical Evidence for Syllabification Patterns in English

  University of Utah Student Conference in Linguistics, **talk**
- 2017 Jenica Jessen and **Sara Ng** *Musical Evidence for Syllabification Patterns of Highly Moraic Structures in English*Undergraduate Research Symposium, University of Utah, **poster**

## RESEARCH POSITIONS

2023-2024	2023 UW Linguistics Fund Award; Research Assistant PI: Richard Wright
Summer 2023	Meta Reality Labs; Research Scientist Intern Host: Christi Miller
Summer 2022	Meta Reality Labs; Research Scientist Intern Host: Christi Miller
2021-2022	US National Institutes of Health, grant NIH R01 DC006014; $Research\ Assistant$ PI: Richard Wright
2021-2022	Google Federated Assistant, Federated Learning; Software Engineering Intern Host: Andrew Hard
2019-2020	US National Science Foundation, grant IIS-1617176; Research Assistant PIs: Mari Ostendorf, Richard Wright
Summer 2019	Google Core Assistant, Pygmalion; Linguist Intern Host: Katie Vadella

2017-2018 University of Washington Linguistics; Departmental Research Assistant

PI: Sharon Hargus

### PATENT APPLICATIONS

2023 Sara Ng, Melinda Anderson, Poornima Shankar, Setare Hajarolasvadi, Katherine Chase,

Christi Miller

Use of Biometric Signals to Personalize Audio

Application No. 18 104701

2023 Sara Ng, Melinda Anderson, Poornima Shankar, Setare Hajarolasvadi, Katherine Chase

Modifying Audio for Presentation to a User Based on a Determined Location of an Audio System Presenting the Audio

Application No. 18 162847

2023 Christi Miller, **Sara Ng**, Calvin Murdock, Nils Thomas Fritiof Lunner, William Owen Brimijoin II,

Vamsi Krishna Ithapu

Estimation Of Hearing Loss of a User from Interactions with a Local Environment by the User

Identified from Captured Audio and Information Describing the Local Area

Application No. 18 162847

### **TEACHING**

### as Instructor of Record

2023 Winter	LING 450/550: Introduction to Linguistic Phonetics
2022 Spring	LING 472: Introduction to Computational Linguistics
2020 Summer	LING 473: Basics For Computational Linguistics

### Teaching Assistanceships

2020 Fall	LING 450: Introduction to Linguistic Phonetics
2019 Spring	CSE 472: Introduction to Computational Linguistics

2018 Fall LING 570: Shallow Processing Techniques for Natural Language Processing

2018 Spring LING 269: Swearing and Taboo Language

### Graderships

2020 Winter	LING 451: Phonology I
2019 Spring	LING 452: Phonology II
2019 Winter	LING 451: Phonology I

## Curriculum Development

2019 Winter Staff assistanceship converting LING 553 (Experimental Phonetics),

LING 450 (Phonetics), and ASL Program course materials to online format

### **Guest Lectures**

2019 25 Oct	LING 550 (Phonetics I): Reading Spectrograms
2019 21 Aug	LING 473 (Compling Basics): Formal Grammars & Parsing

2019 23 May LING 200 (Intro. Linguistics): What is Computational Linguistics?

### GRADUATE COURSEWORK

#### Computational **Theoretical** LING 566: Syntax for Computational Linguistics LING 532: Sociolinguistics I LING 567: Knowledge Engineering for NLP LING 550: Intro. Phonetics LING 570: Shallow Processing Methods for NLP LING 553: Experimental Phonetics LING 571: Deep Processing Methods for NLP LING 507: Syntactic Theory I LING 572: Advanced Statistical NLP LING 579: Semantic Theory II LING 575: NLP Ethics LING 580: Context and Speech Variation LING 575: Spoken Dialogue Systems LING 580: Experimental Phonology LING 575: Analyzing Neural Language Models LING 580: Bias in ASR ECE 511: Statistical Learning LING 580: Voice Quality ECE 596: Conversational Systems and AI GPA 3.9

## GRANTS AND AWARDS

2023	Excellence in Linguistic Research Graduate Fellowship
	University of Washington
2018	Travel Scholarship for Second Ethics in Natural Language Processing Workshop
	North American Chapter of the ACL
2017	Top Scholar Award
	University of Washington Graduate School
2017	UROP Small Research Grant
	University of Utah Undergraduate Research Opportunities Program
2013	President's Scholarship
	University of Utah

## SERVICE

2022	Peer mentor, Undergraduate seminar on graduate school application process
2021	Consultant, High school entrepreneurship competition project
2021	Editor, University of Washington Working Papers in Linguistics
2020	Student Volunteer, Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL)
2020	Organizing Committee Member, Northwest Linguistics Conference (NWLC)
2020	Reviewer, NWLC
2020	Proctor, North American Computational Linguistics Open Competition
2020	Consultant, Undergraduate senior capstone in speech translation
2019	President, Linguistics Society of the University of Washington (LSUW)
2019	Student Volunteer, North American Chapter of the ACL
2018	Vice President, LSUW

## SKILLS

## Computer Languages

- $\bullet$  Python
- R
- $\bullet$  Matlab
- $\bullet \ HTML/CSS/JavaScript$
- $\bullet$  Java

## **Machine Learning**

- $\bullet$  pytorch
- $\bullet$  tensorflow
- Scikit-learn

# Linguistic Tools

- Praat
- NLTK
- $\bullet$  Kaldi
- Electroglottography

## Natural Languages

- French (basic)
- Spanish (basic)
- Toisan Chinese (heritage)